# ZAID ISMAIL SOFTWARE ENGINEER AND CIVIL ENGINEERING GRADUATE

Durban, South Africa | P: +27828965760 | zaidismail031@gmail.com

LinkedIn: https://linkedin.com/in/zaid-ismail-0957a61b1

**GitHub:** https://github.com/zaid-ismail031 **Personal Website:** https://zaidismail.co.za

## **ABOUT ME**

Organized, detail-oriented STEM graduate with experience in web development, IT management and Civil Engineering. Strong written and verbal communication skills. A quick learner and a great problem solver.

**Skills:** Python, C, C++, Java, C#, PHP, JavaScript, HTML/CSS, Django, Flask, Node.js (MERN stack), Git, Octave/MATLAB, Microsoft Excel

#### **PROJECTS**

## Twitter Clone (Django)

- Developed a simple clone of Twitter using Django, a Python-based full-stack framework.
- Users can create posts, "like" posts, edit posts and follow other users.
- Deployed the web application on an AWS EC2 instance.
- Gunicorn is used to serve the Django application, while Nginx acts as a reverse proxy. Nginx accepts incoming connections and redirects these requests to Gunicorn, except for static files, which Nginx handles itself.
- The web application can be viewed and interacted with here: <a href="http://54.212.21.178/">http://54.212.21.178/</a>

# **Stock Trading (Django)**

- Developed a stock trading web application using Django, a Python-based full-stack framework.
- Users can demo-trade with real-life stocks.
- Users can view charts showing up-to-date share prices of popular stocks.
- There is an RSS feed showing relevant news, to aid users in their trading strategies.
- A demo can be viewed here: https://youtu.be/bilbHaLgHi4

## Car Rental (NodeJS)

- Developed a back-end and API for a car rental app using MongoDB, Express, NodeJS, and vanilla JavaScript.
- MongoDB is used alongside Mongoose for database design and management.
- A demo can be viewed here: https://youtu.be/gOxp-XhPD\_q

## Image Classifier Neural Network (Python)

- A trained neural network that can classify images between plane, car, bird, cat, deer, dog, frog, ship or truck.
- The model was trained using an 8-layer neural network with 10 epochs.
- The model has an accuracy of 64%.

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

## **Multiple Projects**

Open-Source Contributor

Aug 2022 - Present

- Refactored code in the Xenia Xbox 360 emulator project, written in C++.
- Contributed to the documentation of Scrapy, a Python web-scraping framework.

- Refactored code in DevilutionX, a source port of the action role-playing videogame Diablo and its expansion Diablo: Hellfire.
- Replaced icons on the frontend of Oppia, Google's open-source education platform.

## Power Builder's Supplies - Durban, South Africa

IT Manager

Jan 2022 - Sep 2022

- Digitized business operations, by creating a website and a custom mailbox.
- Set up a point-of-sale system to record retail transactions.
- Set up the business LAN, computers, printers, and security cameras.
- Set up a data pipeline using Apache Kafka, including data visualization tools to better inform business decisions.

# DE Consultants - Durban, South Africa

Civil Engineering Intern

Jun 2021 - Aug 2021

- Designed a floor slab for a client.
- Prepared engineering drawings using AutoCAD.
- Oversaw the construction of columns for a double storey concrete building.
- Automated several processes, including archival of completed projects, using Python.

## Syntax Co. - Durban, South Africa

Backend Developer

Feb 2021 – Apr 2021

- Spearheaded the company's most expensive project (a car rental web application), resulting in a 200% month-on-month increase in revenue.
- Coded a back-end and API for the car rental app using NodeJS.
- Ensured completion within two months (as per the client's request).

#### **HackerOne**

Freelance Cyber Security Researcher

Jul 2020 - Aug 2020

- Discovered a valid security vulnerability on a Sony-owned web application and submitted it to Sony's Vulnerability Disclosure Program.
- Received a "Secure@Sony 2020" T-Shirt as a reward.

## FORMAL EDUCATION

## University of KwaZulu-Natal - Durban, South Africa

Jan 2017 - Dec 2021

Bachelor of Science in Engineering (with Honours), Civil Engineering

- Completed eight Mathematics courses involving calculus, linear algebra, mathematical systems and statistics.
- Completed a dissertation on the flood attenuation function of artificial wetlands, which required data analysis and mathematical modelling.
- Planned the construction of a structural steel warehouse for the course's final design project.
- Graduated with a 65% average.

## **CERTIFICATES**

# Stanford University – Online

Jun 2022

Machine Learning

- Learned and applied several machine learning concepts including supervised learning, unsupervised learning, linear regression, logistic regression, gradient descent, neural networks and the SVM (support vector machine) algorithm.
- Implemented machine learning algorithms using Octave, a high-level programming language that is specialized for numerical computation and linear algebra.

## AWS-DEV-13: Building Modern .NET Applications on AWS

- Familiarized myself with ASP.NET.
- Gained familiarity with "serverless" web development.
- Deployed .NET web applications with services like Amazon S3 and Amazon EC2.
- Learned how to implement API authentication on Amazon API Gateway using Amazon Cognito.

# **Harvard University - Online**

Mar 2021

CS50's Web Programming with Python and JavaScript

- Gained proficiency in creating web applications using Django.
- · Created interactive web pages using JavaScript.
- · Learned how to use HTML5 and CSS.
- Built a stock trading web application, utilizing a REST API, that allows users to demo-trade stocks.

## **Harvard University - Online**

Jul 2020

CS50's Introduction to Computer Science

- Learned how to program using C and Python by completing practical assignments.
- Learned the fundamentals of computer science.
- Utilized low-level C functions such as pointers and dynamic memory allocation (using "malloc()" and "free()").
- Developed a blog web application using the Flask web development framework.

# Dale Carnegie - Durban, South Africa

Jun 2015

Generation Next Course

- Learned effective methods of teamwork and communication.
- Improved my public speaking skills and had to give presentations in front of sizeable crowds.

## **ADDITIONAL**

**Interests:** Videogames, technology, soccer, science fiction, history, geopolitics, economics, humanitarianism

Languages: English, Afrikaans

## **REFERENCES**

Muhammad Mia (Software Engineer/Founder – Syntax Co.): +31659367181

Salim Ebrahim (Business Owner – Power Builder's Supplies): +27837860848